Guide to the King Family Papers 1754-1908 MS 350
New-York Historical Society
King Family Papers
1754-1908
New-York Historical Society
MS 350
2 Linear feet
The collection consists of correspondence, printed matter, and genealogical material, etc. of the descendents of Richard King (1718 - 1775) and Rufus King (1755 - 1827). The collection concerns the King family, other families directly descended from them, and some collateral branches. The following individuals are comparatively well documented: Rufus King (1755 - 1853), John Alsop King (1788 - 1867), Charles Ray King (1813 - 1901), Nancy Wharton (Fisher) King (1826 - 1905),and Charles F. Lennig (1836 - d.)
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Scope and Contents note
The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence (mostly among family members), and various legal and financial documents. The papers delineate personal and social lives; they deal to a much lesser extent with public, political and business affairs. They document many aspects of the lives of women and men: birth, marriage and death, daily activities and events, visits and travels, and interpersonal relations among families and friends.
There is genealogical material, mostly in the form of hand-drawn family trees. There are also inventories of personal property, memorabilia, such as visiting cards, drawings, newspapers, clippings, and photographs.
Unless specified in the inventory as copies (transcriptions), documents are assumed to be original.
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Further information about the King Family is located at the New-York Historical Society within the Rufus King Papers and the Erving-King Family Papers.
Arragement
Missing Title
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: General Family Materials
The King Family Papers are divided into two series. Series I is divided into twelve subseries based on members of the King Family. Series II is organized by subject.
Historical note
This collection records the history of the King family from mid-eighteenth century to the early twentieth century. The papers concern the King family; other families descended directly from Richard King and Rufus King, and some collateral branches and connecting families are included.
Many of their descendents and relatives were prominent in politics, diplomacy, military service, law, business, banking and letters; particularly in Maine, Pennsylvania, Massachusetts, New York, New Jersey, and Great Britain. They were well-to-do, and connected by marriage with other distinguished and prominent New York families.
Rufus King (1755 – 1827) was an American lawyer, politician, and diplomat. He was born in Scarborough, Maine, then a section of Massachusetts, the eldest son of farmer-merchant Richard and Isabella King. He attended Harvard and briefly served in the military during the Revolutionary War. He was a delegate for Massachusetts to the Continental Congress. He also attended the Constitutional Convention and was one of the signers of the United States Constitution. He represented New York in the United States Senate, served as Minister to Britain, and was the Federalist candidate for Vice President two times and later Federalist candidate for President of the United States.
The lives of Rufus King's children and grandchildren are comparatively well documented in this collection. James Gore King (1791-1853), son of Rufus King, attended school in England and France while his father was ambassador to London. After graduating from Harvard and studying law, he became a banker, and in 1818 with his brother-in-law, Archibald Gracie, Jr. established in Liverpool the firm of King and Gracie.
John Alsop King (1788 – 1867), son of Rufus King, practiced law in New York City. John King's law career was interrupted by a stint as a cavalry lieutenant in the War of 1812. After the war, he ventured into politics. King was a member of the New York State Assembly and later the New York State Senate. King was elected as a Whig to the 31st United States Congress. He also served a short term as Governor of New York from 1837-1838.
Charles King (1789 – 1867), son of Rufus King, was a captain of a volunteer regiment in the early part of the War of 1812, and served in the 1814 New York Assembly. He was married to Eliza Gracie, the daughter of shipping magnate Archibald Gracie. He served as the ninth president of Columbia College (now Columbia University), holding the role from 1849 to 1864.
The King Family Papers also include those of John Alsop (1724 - 1794), Charles Ray King (1813 - 1901), Nancy Wharton King (1826 - 1905), Charles F. Lenning (1836 - d.) as well as additional family correspondence.
Genealogical information of the King family are located in Series II.
Genealogy.; New York (N.Y.); Abolitionists -- United States.; Illinois; Lumber trade -- United States.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1783-1865.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States -- Politics and government -- 19th century.; Philadelphia (Pa.); Letters (correspondence); Americans -- England -- London.; Upper class -- New York (State) -- New York.; Americans -- Foreign countries.; King, Rufus, 1755-1827; Troup, Robert, 1757-1832; King, James G. (James Gore), 1791-1853; King, Charles, 1789-1867; King, John Alsop, 1788-1867; Alsop, John, 1724-1794; Fisher, James Cowles, 1817-1896; Johnson, Lawrence, 1801-1860; King, Charles Ray, 1813-1901; King, Nancy Wharton Fisher, 1826-1905; Lennig, Charles Frederick, -1836; King, Mary Lennig Fisher, 1844-1900; Lennig, Millicent Gaw Johnson, 1882-1919; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849.; Davis, Matthew L. (Matthew Livingston), 1773-1850
- Series I: Correspondence, 1761-1908 (Box 3, Box 2, Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence, mostly among family members.
  Unless specified in the inventory as copies (transcriptions), documents are assumed to be original. The series is organized in a loosely chronological order.
  - Subseries 1: John Alsop, 1761-1786
    Biographical note
    John Alsop (1724 – 1794) was an American merchant and politician from New York City during the American Revolution. He was a delegate for New York to the Continental Congress, and the father-in-law of Rufus King. His correspondence includes letters to Philip Livingston and Thomas Wharton and a letter from his daughter, Mary Alsop King (1769 - 1819).
    - Correspondence from John Alsop, 1761-1777 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence to John Alsop, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2: Rufus King, 1773-1826
    Rufus King (1755 – 1827) was an American lawyer, politician, and diplomat. He was a delegate for Massachusetts to the Continental Congress. He also attended the Constitutional Convention and was one of the signers of the United States Constitution. He represented New York in the United States Senate, served as Minister to Britain, and was a Federalist candidate for Vice President (1804, 1808) and later President of the United States (1816). The majority of King's correspondence is to Dr. Robert Southgate (his brother-in-law) during the revolutionary period and later to Robert Troup (1756 - 1832).
    - Correspondence from Rufus King, 1773-1779 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence from Rufus King, 1780-1793 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence from Rufus King, 1794-1800 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence from Rufus King, 1801-1824 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence to Rufus King, 1785-1800 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence to Rufus King, 1801-1806 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence to Rufus King, 1815-1826 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence: Rufus King, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence: Rufus King (Transcriptions), 1789-1821 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 3: John Alsop King, 1803-1867
    John Alsop King (1788 – 1867) was the son of Rufus King. He was a member of the New York State Assembly and later the New York State Senate. King was elected as a Whig to the 31st United States Congress. He also served a short term as Governor of New York from 1837-1838. The majority of correspondence is with his son, Charles Ray King and his brothers.
    - Correspondence from John Alsop King, 1826-1828 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence to John Alsop King, 1803-1835 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence to John Alsop King, 1836-1867 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence: John Alsop King, Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 4: Charles King, 1821-1825
    Charles King (1789 – 1867) was the son of Rufus King. He served as the ninth president of Columbia College (now Columbia University), holding the role from 1849 to 1864. The majority of correspondence is with his brother, John Alsop King.
    - Correspondence from Charles King, 1821-1825 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence to Charles King, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
      General
      Includes a letter from Albert Gallatin to Matthew L. Davis, dated Feb. 6, 1801, discussing the United States presidential election of 1800.
  - Subseries 5: James Gore King, 1823-1853
    James Gore King (1791-1853) was the son of Rufus King. After graduating from Harvard and studying law, he became a banker, and in 1818 with his brother-in-law, Archibald Gracie, Jr. established in Liverpool the firm of King and Gracie. The majority of correspondence with his father, Rufus King, and his brother, Charles King.
    - Correspondence from James Gore King, 1823-1853 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence from James Gore King (Transcriptions), 1824 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence to James Gore King, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Subseries 6: Lawrence Johnson, 1837-1854
    Lawrence Johnson (1801 – 1860) was born in England and emigrated to the United States of America in his youth. He became an eminent stereotyper and type-founder in Philadelphia and one of the most extensive and successful type-founders in the United States. He is the grandfather of Millicent (Johnson) King Lennig (1882 - 1919). The majority of correspondence is with his children.
    - Correspondence to Lawrence Johnson, 1837-1854 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 7: Charles Ray King, 1836-1898
    Charles Ray King (1813 - 1901) was the son of John Alsop King and the grandson of Rufus King. He was first married to Hannah Wharton (Fisher) King in 1839, and later after her death married her sister, Nancy Wharton (Fisher) King, in 1872. He was a physician who resided in Bucks County, Pennsylvania. The majority of correspondence is with his father, John Alsop King (1788 - 1867) and his children.
    - Correspondence from Charles Ray King, 1836-1882 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence to Charles Ray King, 1872-1873 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence to Charles Ray King, 1874-1889 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence to Charles Ray King, 1890-1898 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence to Charles Ray King, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 8: Nancy Wharton (Fisher) King, 1873-1875
    Nancy Wharton (Fisher) King (1826 - d.) was the second wife of Charles Ray King and the sister of his first wife, Hannah. The majority of correspodence is between immediate family members.
    - Correspondence to Nancy Wharton (Fisher) King, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence to Nancy Wharton (Fisher) King, 1873-1875 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 9: Charles F. Lennig, 1866-1893
    Charles Frederick Lennig (1836 - 1868) was the son-in-law of Charles Ray King (1813 - 1901). Lennig married King's daughter, Mary Fisher King (1844 - 1900). Lennig was an attorney in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. The majority of correspondence is with his wife, Mary Fisher (King) Lennig (1844 - 1900).
    - Correspondence from Charles F. Lennig, 1866-1875 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence to Charles F. Lennig, 1854-1893 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence to Charles F. Lennig, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 10: Mary Fisher (King) Lennig, 1872-1873
    Mary Fisher (King) Lennig (1844 - 1900) was the daughter of Charles Ray King (1813 - 1901) and the wife of Charles F. Lennig (1836 - 1868). She lived in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. The majority of correspondence is with her husband, Charles F. Lennig, and her father, Charles Ray King.
    - Correspondence to Mary Fisher (King) Lennig, 1872-1873 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 11: Millicent (Johnson) King Lennig, 1908
    Millicent Gaw (Johnson) King Lennig (1874 - 1919) was the granddaughter of Lawrence Johnson (1801 - 1860) and the daughter-in-law of Charles F. Lennig (1836 - 1868) and Mary Fisher (King) Lennig (1844 - 1900). She married Rufus King Lennig (1874 - d.) in 1913 and lived in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. All correspondence is with her cousin, Morris W. Johnson.
    - Correspondence to Millicent (Johnson) King Lennig, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 12: Unidentified Correspondence, 1832-1877, undated
    - Unidentified Correspondence, 1832-1877, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series II: General Family Materials, 1803-1900 (Box 3)
  Series II contains voluminous genealogical material, much in the form of repetitious handwritten notations and handwritten family trees. There are also inventories of personal property, memorabilia, such as visiting cards, drawings, newspapers, clippings, and photographs. There are documents relating to Rufus King's notes on the following: an act to provide for certain surviving officers and soldiers of the Revolutionary Army (1817), and the admission of Illinois and Missouri to the United States (1818). There are also biographical/obituary materials for John Alsop King (1817 - 1900) and James Cowles Fisher (1756 - 1840).
  - Rufus King: Financial and Legal Documents, 1803-1820 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Rufus King: H.R. 8 "A Bill to Provide for Certain Surviving Officers and Soldiers of the Revolutionary Army" (Draft), 1817 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Rufus King: Notes on the Bills for the Admission of the States of Missouri and Illinois, 1818 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Memorial on Behalf of Archibald Gracie, 1817 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - James Cowles Fisher: "Memorandum of my Birth and Connections", 1832 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Charles Ray King: Passport, 1834 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - James Gore King: Daniel Webster Speech Notes, 1835 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Historical and Geneological Notes on the King Family and Descendents, 1755-1900, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Geneological Charts of King Descendents, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Papers Concerning the Death of John Alsop King, 1900, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)